I would imagine that many of the people
who watch my videos have at least heard
of game B and I've noticed that there
seems to be a perception which I don't
agree with personally but anyway doesn't
matter whether I agree or not the
perception exists that the game B
conversation is somewhat impenetrable
for you know just average folk kind of
thing and that in order to get into it
you've had to commit to watching dozens
and dozens of hours of videos and
listening to podcasts and so on in order
to acquaint yourself with B with the
idea sufficiently to understand it and I
mean there is some truth to that you can
go as deep into it as you want to but I
think many of the key concepts that are
the foundation of game via actually
pretty straightforward to understand and
so I thought it might be a good idea to
make a series of short videos to explain
in fairly straightforward tones some of
those key concepts I'm gonna begin by
outlining what game a is because game B
is most easily talked about in terms of
its contrasts with what game a is and so
in this first video I'm gonna sort of
unpack a little bit the idea of what
game a is all about what the fundamental
characteristics of game a are and how
game B will differ from that and I'll go
through some of those one-by-one in
future videos so the game a if you've
played Sid Meier's Civilization then
you've got a pretty decent handle on
what game a is I think they're actually
quite closely analogous and so in the
game civilization you start off at a
little tiny village and you go scouting
around you can't see any of the
surrounding territories you have to go
scouting around and see what's there and
you come across the sources and you have
to cultivate them and manage them your
population starts to grow you
investigate technologies you have to
distribute resources so that your
population gets fed there are bands of
barbarians wandering around who want to
kill you and take over your city so you
have to defend yourself against those in
the early part of the game as the game
develops and this is where game a really
comes in as the game develops you start
to bump into other fledgling
civilizations and
um in order to maintain the integrity of
your own civilization you have to do
several things that I've already said it
but a cultivator is also so that you can
feed everyone and you have to generate
loyal seeds to the civilization which
you do by developing a culture you need
to develop an economy so that there is
trade going on things for people to do
you need to develop a religion so that
people have you know a a this is part of
loyalty to the culture a broader
involvement in in the culture as a whole
not just with their immediate circles
and you have to cultivate a military
otherwise you get taken over by the
other civilizations and so this is a
pretty good analogy for what game a is
you know back in the day before there
were civilizations hunter-gatherer
tribes spread across the world took over
every available niche and became the
apex predator in each and every niche
but at some point they became so
successful they started bumping into
each other and all the territory was
already occupied and so there was
nowhere else to go and so one of two
things that had to have to either start
killing each other all the time or they
figure out a way to exist in larger
bands that they previously had done and
so this is this as the beginning of game
a was the bumping together a small
tribes who had to figure out ways to
exist in larger groups where the
intimacy of relationship can no longer
bleep be the glue that holds them
together another way of doing that needs
to be come up with and that's kind of
game a and so game a is what we have
been doing for the last twelve thousand
years and of course there have been very
very very many variations on game a
there's been lots of different religions
lots of different ways of treating women
and slaves and so on lots of different
ways of accessing water lots of
different engineering skills lots of
different technologies all of that kind
of thing there are many ways in which
game a has been extremely successful I
mean obviously different tribes had
different skill sets and different
knowledge about different things and so
if you can figure out a way to
collaborate effectively then all of a
sudden the civilization as a whole has
access to all of the skills that all of
the tribes and all of them
that rule the tribes had access to and
so there are huge advantages in this in
this collaboration across scale but
there are also significant externalities
that are produced by gamej and I guess
in a way you could say that our current
civilization is the winner thus far of
game a because the only one that has not
collapsed every civilization in history
has collapsed the Greeks the Romans the
Ottomans the Egyptians the Mayans the
Incans the Sumerians you know all of
these civilizations are gone now and
ours is the latest evolution the latest
refinement of game a but game a is
characterized by certain things you know
all of these evolutions of game a are
characterized by three basic principles
and that's what I want to go into in
future videos each of these things might
be might look like from a game B
perspective you know game a has in in
three basic ways which I'll go into a
minute has always been basically the
same but what's different now is the
level the scale the efficiency of our
technology and so our ability to extract
our ability to make or our ability to
pollute has now got to the point where
we've actually become a threat to
ourselves and not only to ourselves but
to a lot of the rest of the life on the
planet as well and so these
externalities that have always existed
in game a have now been magnified and
amplified by technology to the point
where they are a threat to us a genuine
threat to our very existence and this is
why you need to figure out a new game to
play game B right whatever game B is you
know what it actually is you know it but
but but a new game with different
parameters different fundamentals so the
three things I'm going to talk about in
future videos the three characteristics
that have always underpinned every
iteration of game a are complicatedness
and so using complicated systems
hierarchies government rules laws these
kinds of things to manage complex
systems the environment ecosystems human
beings Society and so on and there's a
fundamental incompatibility between
these
two modes of organization so that's one
second one is a top-down broadcast
modality of sense making and
decision-making and so a king or an
emperor or a government or whatever it
might be decides what's going on in the
world what's best for the civilization
tells everybody else what to do and they
follow those instructions and so your
role as a member of society is simply to
basically listen and to do as you're
told right so that's that's broadcast
and then the third one is rival richness
and this is basically a response to the
fact that you know things are limited
you don't have an infinite amount of
space to grow food on you don't have an
infinite amount of water you know this
kind of thing and so there is always
competition over scarce resources and
this leads to a modality within the
civilization within the society of rival
richness and this runs extremely deep so
these three notions of rivalry sness and
broadcast modality and complicatedness
are enduring features of gaming and it
is these things which need to be turned
on their heads in game be into anti
rival resinous distributed decentralized
sense making and decision making
processes and the use of complex
decision-making process in order to
handle the complexity of the systems
with which we need to deal so I think
that's about all I need to say for this
one and I look forward to seeing you in
future ones thanks for watching